Sooren Simon Alexander Papers and Dental Instruments MS149
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
Sooren Simon Alexander Papers and Dental Instruments
1918 -- 1922
1918 -- 1969
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
Alexander, Sooren Simon
MS149
0.75 Linear Feet
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.
Arrangement
This collection is organized in two series: Papers; and Dental Instruments
Biographical / Historical
Dr. Sooren Simon Alexander was born February 25, 1897 in Armenia as Sooren Simon Alexanian. His family escaped the Armenian genocide when he was eight years old and moved to Worcester, Massachusetts. Alexander changed his last name in 1921 when he began practicing dentistry. He died November 28, 1978 in Worcester, Massachusetts.
Alexander graduated from the Tufts College Dental School in 1921. He practiced dentistry fifty-five years and was a member of the both the American and the Massachusetts Dental Associations, the North East Dental Society and the Worcester District Dental Society. He was a member of Athelstan Lodge of Masons, a 32nd degree Mason, a member of the Scottish Rite Bodies, A Shriner, and a member of Aletheia Grotto.
Alexander was married to Alice Juskalian and had two daughters, Harriet and Beverly.
Custodial History
Donated by Alexander's daughter, Harriet Alexander.
Related Materials
UP143, Dental School Yearbook, DCA
UA020, Dental School Records, DCA
Scope and Contents
This collection includes class notebooks from the dental school, a dental yearbook, a dental commencement program and photograph as well as dental instruments used by Dr. Alexander in his dental practice.
Alumni collections; Dental history; Dentistry; University history; Tufts University -- History
- Papers, 1918 -- 1969; 1918 -- 1922; MS149.001; 0.25 Linear Feet
  Scope and Contents
  This series includes class notebooks from Dr. Alexander's studies at Tufts College Dental School, a 1921 Dental School yearbook and his commencement program and photograph.
  Arrangement
  This series is arranged chronologically.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Open for research.
  - Dental Drawings, 1918 -- 1921; MS149.001.001.00001 (Box 1)
  - Physiology notebook, 1918; MS149.001.001.00002 (Box 1)
  - Physical diagnosis and oral surgery notebook, 1920 -- 1921; MS149.001.001.00003 (Box 1)
  - Dental School Commencement Program, 1921; MS149.001.001.00004 (Box 1)
  - Commencement photograph, 1921; MS149.001.001.00005 (Box 1)
  - Dental School yearbook, 1921; MS149.001.001.00006 (Box 1)
  - Photo, Alexander in his dental office, 1922; MS149.001.001.00007 (Box 1)
    Rubber irrigation bulb (MS149.002.002.00003) shown in picture.
  - Membership cards, 1952 -- 1969; MS149.001.001.00008 (Box 1)
    Dental Association and Mason Lodge cards
- Dental instruments, 1922 -- 1959; MS149.002; 0.5 Linear Feet
  This series includes instruments Dr. Alexander used in his dental practice.
  This series is arranged as found.
  - Engraved name plate, 1922; MS149.002.002.00001 (Box 2)
  - Model scalers and gold fillings, 1922; MS149.002.002.00002 (Box 2)
  - Rubber irrigation bulb, 1922; MS149.002.002.00003 (Box 2)
    Pictured in MS149.001.001.00007
  - Drill bits and attachments in wood block, 1922; MS149.002.002.00004 (Box 2)
  - Instruments, 1922; MS149.002.002.00005 (Box 2)
  - Instruments, 1922; MS149.002.002.00006 (Box 2)
  - Instruments in green felt cases, 1950 -- 1959; MS149.002.002.00007 (Box 2)